Finding Aid for the Page Smith Papers LSC.0620
UCLA Library Special Collections
Page Smith papers
circa 1952-1964
UCLA Library Special Collections
Smith, Page, 1917-1995
LSC.0620
15.0 Linear Feet (15 cartons)
Restrictions on Access
Unprocessed collection. Material is unavailable for access. Please contact Special Collections reference (spec-coll@library.ucla.edu) for more information.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
The Page Smith Papers were acquired in 2004 from the Page Smith family and in cooperation with the Special Collections and Archives of the Library, University of California, Santa Cruz.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9964152053606533
Biography
Historian (Charles) Page Smith was born on Septermber 16, 1917 in Baltimore, Maryland; B.A. Dartmouth College (1940); Ph.D. Harvard University (1951) under the direction of Samuel Eliot Morison. Assistant professor of history at the University of California, Los Angeles (1952); associate professor (1956); professor (1963). In 1964 Smith left UCLA to become the founding Provost of Cowell College, University of California, Santa Cruz and resigned from the university in 1973. In 1963 he won the Bancroft Prize for his 1962 biography of John Adams. Smith died on August 28, 1995 in Santa Cruz, California.
Smith, Page.
- Professional and publication files., 1939-2000; Series 1.; 6 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes: unpublished papers, manuscript drafts, reprints, book reviews, research notes, notes for courses, scripts for talks given by Page Smith, subject files, correspondence, biographical materials, professional association and conference materials, newspaper articles by Page Smith.
  - Biographical., c.1964-2000; 1 folder (Box 3)
    articles (newspaper, newsletter, journal) and tributes to Page Smith.
  - Course lectures., c.1975; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Festival of nonviolence., 1973; no date; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Incoming correspondence to Page Smith., 1947-1996; 1 folder (Box 3)
    Primarily photocopies.
  - Interviews with Page Smith., 1953; 1970; no date (Box 3)
    Interview scripts including radio interviews.
  - Outgoing correspondence by Page Smith., 1941-1996; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Rosenstock-Huessy, Eugene., c.1939-1995; 1 folder (Box 3)
    Correspondence, notes, programs for talks, and short papers by various authors about the life and influence of Rosenstock-Huessy.
    General note
    Historian and social philosopher Eugene Rosenstock-Huessy (b.1888-d.1973) taught at Dartmouth College while Page Smith was an undergraduate student at Dartmouth. One of Page Smith's early mentors, he exerted a significant influence over Page Smith's thought and work.
  - Southampton Summer Conference: Project Open. [Westport, Connecticut], 1974; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Talks by Page Smith -- correspondence., c.1954-1995; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Talks by Page Smith -- notes, scripts, and programs., c.1939-1992; no date.; 2 folders (Box 3)
    Primarily photocopies; includes timeline for talks given between 1953-1995.
  - UCLA., 1952; 1971; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - William James Association., c.1975-1976; 1 folder (Box 3)
  - "God's Voice and the American Revolution.", 1 folder (Box 4)
    Photocopy of a paper by Page Smith.
  - "History must be told.", 1954 Jan; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Text written by Page Smith for a documentary on U. S. history. Also includes notes, correspondence, and a commentary on the nature and significance of history and its treatment in academia.
  - "John Adams" research files., c.1957-1971; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Includes notes on the period 1773-1813.
  - "John Adams," volume I typed manuscript., c.1962; 14 folders (Box 4)
    Chapters I-XLIII, pages 1-949, and volume I notes. Contains publisher's edits.
    See box #5 for volume II manuscript and index.
  - Blacks in 19th century United States., n.d.; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Copies of Page Smith's research notes and writings regarding African Americans in the United States during the 19th and early 20th centuries.
  - Democracy., c.1947; no date; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Photocopies. Includes notes; quoted materials from early historians; and a paper by Page Smith, "Sam Adams: The revolutionary mind."
  - Education., c.1948; 1981-1984; no date; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Primarily photocopies. Includes clippings of newspaper articles and papers by Page Smith pertaining to education and academia.
  - Essays., no date; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Primarily photocopies. Typescripts of essays by Page Smith on various topics.
  - History., c.1948; no date; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Photocopies of research materials and papers by Page Smith and others pertaining to history. Includes a paper, "Faith of an historian," by Samuel Eliot Morison.
  - Los Alamos Lunar Base Workshop., 1979-1984; 4 folders (Box 4)
    Conference materials including conference planning, biographical sketches, correspondence, print articles about space and the moon, NASA report "Lunar Surface Return" (March 1984), and conference working papers.
    Conference held April 23-27, 1984 in Los Alamos, New Mexico.
  - Master reprints by Page Smith., c.1949-1992; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - National Association of Scholars -- curriculum., c.1990-1992; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Includes newspaper articles pertaining to college curriculum and the National Association of Scholars. Also includes a typescript (photocopy) of a policy draft proposal by the Stanford chapter.
  - Philosophy., no date; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Notes and writings on various philosophers.
  - Preface to "Humanity made to order.", no date; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Photocopy of edited typescript of Page Smith's preface to "Humanity Made to Order" by Harry Stekoll (L. Furman, inc., publisher 1937).
  - Short stories., c.1940-1949; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Photocopies of short stories by Page Smith.
  - U.S. history., c.1946-1953; no date; 1 folder (Box 4)
    Primarily photocopies. Notes and texts by Page Smith and others on U.S. history.
  - "A new age now begins..." first draft., c.1974-1975; 6 folders (Box 5)
    Includes original typescript and photocopies of the introduction and Volumes 1-5. Missing chapters: volume 1 chapters 1-2, 5-9, 11; volume 4 chapters 4-5; volume 5 chapter 3. See box 6 for volumes 6-10, bibliographic note, and index.
    Full title: "A new age now begins: A people's history of the United States." Published in 1976 as a two-volume set. Six more volumes, 3-8, of "A People's History of the United States," each dealing with a different historical era, were published between 1980-1986.
  - "As a city upon a hill" book reviews., 1966 Sep-1967 April; 1 folder (Box 5)
    Many photocopies. Clippings from newspapers and periodicals.
  - "Daughters of the promised land..." book reviews., 1970 Nov-1972 Jan; 1 folder (Box 5)
    Clippings from newspapers and magazines.
    Full title: "Daughters of the promised land, women in American history." Former working title: "Daughters of Zion."
  - "Daughters of the promised land..." galley proofs., c.1969; 4 folders (Box 5)
    Includes table of contents, pages 3-156, postcript, notes, and index.
    Full title: "Daughters of the promised land, women in American history." Working title on galley proofs: "Daughters of Zion."
  - "Daughters of the promised land..." typed manuscript., c.1969; 5 folders (Box 5)
    Photocopy of typed manuscript containing Page Smith's edits. Pages 1-496.
  - "John Adams" book awards., 1963; 1 folder (Box 5)
    Book award announcements and telegram.
  - "John Adams" book reviews., 1962 Sep-1964 July; 1 folder (Box 5)
    Includes clippings of reviews from magazines, journals, and newspapers. See box #8 for more reviews of "John Adams."
  - "John Adams," Volume II typed manuscript., c.1962; 12 folders (Box 5)
    Chapters I-XLIX, pages 950-1843, volume II notes, Volumes I-II index. Includes publisher's edits. See box #4 for manuscript of volume I.
  - "The historian and history" book reviews., 1964 March-Dec; 1 folder (Box 5)
    Newspaper clippings.
  - "A new age now begins..." first draft., c.1974-1975; 12 folders (Box 6)
    Includes original typescript (some photocopies) of Volumes 6-10, bibliographic note, and index. Missing chapters: volume 8 chapters 6-8, 11; volume 9 chapters 6, 11; volume 10 chapters 6, 8. See box 5 for volumes 1-5.
    Full title: "A new age now begins: A people's history of the United States." Published as a two-volume set in 1976. Six more volumes, 3-8, of "A People's History of the United States," each dealing with a different historical era, were published between 1980-1986.
  - "A new age now begins..." publisher's correspondence., c.1975-1976; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - "A new age now begins..." book reviews., c.1971; 1976 Feb-1977 Summer; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Newspaper clippings, magazine reviews, correspondence from the U.S. Naval War College and a book review from the "Naval War College review."
  - "America enters the world..." book reviews., 1985 June; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Clippings from periodicals.
    Full title: "America enters the world: A people's history of the Progressive Era and World War I." Volume 7 of the eight-volume "A people's history of the United States."
  - "Coming of age" drafts., no date; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Includes typed drafts of 29 articles by Page Smith with author's edits. See box #7 and #8 for "Coming of age" clippings.
    "Coming of age" was a weekly column on aging written by Page Smith from August 1988 until March 1992 for Chronicle Features. The syndicated column was published in many papers including the San Francisco Chronicle.
  - "Democracy on trial" book material., no date; 1 folder (Box 6)
    One cartoon.
    Full title: "Democracy on trial: The Japanese American evacuation and relocation in World War II.
  - "Democracy on trial" book reviews., 1995 Aug-Sep; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Photocopies of newspaper clippings. Also includes one letter to Ms. Easley, Page Smith's daughter.
  - "Dissenting opinions: Selected essays" book reviews., 1984 May-Aug; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - "Jefferson: a revealing biography" typescript of chapter XVI., c.1975; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - "Jefferson: a revealing biography" book reviews., c.1976 Aug-1977 Feb; 1 folder (Box 6)
  - "Killing the spirit..." book reviews., 1990 Feb-May; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Newspaper and magazine clippings.
    Full title: Killing the spirit: Higher education in America."
  - "Killing the Spirit..." book tour documents., c.1990 March; 1993 Jan; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Book tour schedule and newspaper clipping.
  - "Old age is another country..." book reviews., 1995 Sep-1996 Jan; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Photocopies of newspaper clippings.
    Full title: "Old age is another country: A traveler's guide."
  - "Redeeming the time..." book review., 1986 Oct; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Photocopy of newspaper clipping.
    Full title: "Redeeming the time: A people's history of the 1920s and the New Deal." Volume 8 of the eight-volume "A people's history of the United States."
  - "The chicken book" typed manuscript., c.1974; 2 folders (Box 6)
    Includes chapters IX-XIV.
    Former working title: "Chicken-Smith." Page Smith co-authored "The chicken book" with Charles Daniel.
  - "The nation comes of age..." book reviews., 1982 Feb; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Full title: "The nation comes of age: A people's history of the ante-bellum years." Volume 4 of the eight-volume "A people's history of the United States."
  - "The rise of industrial America..." book reviews., 1984 March; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Full title: "The rise of industrail America: A people's history of the post-Reconstruction era." Volume 6 of the eight-volume "A people's history of the United States."
  - "The shaping of America..." book reviews., 1980 March-July; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Full title: "The shaping of America: A people's history of the young Republic." Volume 3 of the eight-volume "A people's history of the United States."
  - "Trial by fire..." book reviews., 1982 Nov-Dec; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Full title: "Trial by fire: A people's history of the Civil War and Reconstruction." Volume 5 of the eight-volume "A people's history of the United States."
  - Newspaper article drafts., no date; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Photocopies of 11 typed drafts with author's edits.
  - Newspaper articles by Page Smith., c.1947 Sep-1993 June; 4 folders (Box 6)
    Clippings (some photocopies) of articles by Page Smith on various topics.
  - Scraps of writing by Page Smith., no date; 1 folder (Box 6)
    Primarily photocopies. Typed drafts of short essays on various topics. Includes a list of topics.
  - "Coming of age.", c.1988 Aug-1992 March; 2 folders (Box 7)
    Includes biographical note about Page smith; an article about the column; and clippings (some photocopies). See also "Seniors." See box #8 for more "Coming of age" clippings.
    "Coming of Age" was a weekly column on aging written by Page Smith from August 1988 until March 1992 for Chronicle Features. The syndicated column was published in many papers including the San Francisco Chronicle. It was also published under the title, "Time to live."
  - "Seniors.", c.1990 Feb-1991 Aug; 1 folder (Box 7)
    Page Smith's syndicated column on aging for Chronicle Features was published in many papers including, under the title "Seniors," in the Santa Cruz County Sentinel.
  - "The chicken book" book reviews., c.1975 June-1986 Aug; 1 folder (Box 7)
    newspaper and magazine clippings (some photocopies).
  - "The chicken book" galley proofs., c.1974; 4 folders (Box 7)
    Includes pages 1-57, 75-138, and index. Pages 58-74 missing.
  - "Coming of age.", no date; 1 folder (Box 8)
    Clippings. See box #7 for more "Coming of age" clippings; see also "Seniors."
  - "James Wilson" book reviews., c.1956 Feb-1957 May; 1 folder (Box 8)
    Full title: "James Wilson, founding father, 1742-1798."
  - "John Adams" book reviews., c.1962 Oct-1964 May; 1 folder (Box 8)
    Newspaper clippings. See box #5 for more book reviews of "John Adams."
  - Newspaper articles by Page Smith., no date; 1 folder (Box 8)
    Clippings of articles by Page Smith on various topics. See box #6 for more newspaper articles by Page Smith.
- W. Ward Smith memoir files., 1896-1976, bulk 1920-1944; Series 2.; 2 Linear Feet
  Includes: memoir text (typed from W. Ward Smith dictation), photographs, and publication materials relating to "A letter from my father: the strange, intimate correspondence of W. Ward Smith to his son Page Smith," edited by Page Smith (Morrow, 1976). W. Ward Smith (b.1893-d.1968) was the father of Page Smith.
  - "A letter from my father..." photographs., 1896-1955; 1 folder (Box 1)
    Photographs (46 items) numbered in red pencil and used in the publication, "A letter from my father: The strange, intimate correspondence of W. Ward Smith to his son Page Smith," edited by Page Smith. Includes: images of W. Ward Smith as a child; W. Ward Smith's family; Page Smith; W. Ward Smith's wives and other women in his life; W. Ward Smith's travels; images of New York politicians and businessmen.
    See flat oversized folder on bottom of box.
  - "A letter from my father..." page proofs., 1975-1976; 10 folders (Box 1)
    Two sets of page proofs in page number order. One set in 16 printed (blue print) booklets approximately 31 pages each. Also includes cardboard templates with design layout of front matter (title page, table of contents, and copyright page).
    Full title: "A letter from my father: The strange, intimate correspondence of W. Ward Smith to his son Page Smith" edited by Page Smith.
  - "A letter from my father..." typed transcriptions., c.1926-1943; 6 folders (Box 1)
    W. Ward Smith's memoir repaginated in red pencil with editorial marks and inserted typed explanatory pages by Page Smith. The bulk of the transcriptions covers the years 1920-1930. Includes (repaginated) manuscript pages 1-599. Transcriptions in approximate chronological order by page number; some gaps in pagination. See boxes #2 and 3 for remainder of memoir.
    Portions of W. Ward Smith's memoir were used for the publication, "A letter from my father: The strange, intimate correspondence of W. Ward Smith to his son Page Smith," edited by Page Smith.
  - "A letter from my father..." galley proofs., 1975-1976; 10 folders (Box 1)
    Two sets of galley proofs, one marked "Reader's Set" the other marked "AU's gals." Contain typed and hand-written edits.
  - Letter by W. Ward Smith., 1933; 1 folder (Box 1)
    Page two and three of typed letter written by W. Ward Smith describing travels in China and the Philippines.
  - "A letter from my father..." typed transcriptions., c.1926-1943; 8 folders (Box 2)
    W. Ward Smith's memoir repaginated in red pencil with editorial marks and inserted typed explanatory pages by Page Smith. The bulk of the transcriptions covers the years 1930-1942. Includes photocopies of transcribed correspondence between W. Ward Smith and Page Smith covering the period from 1933 April-July. Includes (repaginated) manuscript pages 600-1383. Transcriptions in approximate chronological order by page number; some gaps in pagination. See boxes #1 and 3 for remainder of memoir.
  - "A letter from my father..." typed transcriptions., c.1926-1943; 1 folder (Box 2)
    Five unpaginated pages of W. Ward Smith's memoir. Includes two pages of a transcribed letter by W. Ward Smith to Page Smith dated October 1929.
  - "A letter from my father..." typed transcriptions., c.1926-1943; 29 folders (Box 2)
    W. Ward Smith's memoir with original pagination. While the bulk of the transcriptions covers the years 1926-1941, the text begins with W. Ward Smith's boyhood (1890s). Includes W. Ward Smith's travels with second wife, Melba, to Japan, China, India, and Egypt. Contains a transcription of W. Ward Smith's resume (age 38), pages 7736-7747. Includes manuscript pages 61-7999. Transcriptions in approximate chronological order by page number; some gaps in pagination. See boxes #1 and 3 for remainder of memoir.
  - "A letter from my father..." typed transcriptions., c.1926-1943; 14 folders (Box 3)
    W. Ward Smith's memoir with original pagination. The bulk of the transcriptions covers the years 1937-1943. Includes manuscript pages 8000-9815. Transcriptions in approximate chronological order by page number; some gaps in pagination. See boxes #1 and 2 for remainder of memoir.